<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An apology for the royal party: written in a letter to a person of the late Councel of State. / By a lover of peace and of his country. With a touch at the pretended plea for the army.</title>
            <author>Evelyn, John, 1620-1706.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 45 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A84168</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E3482</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E763_11</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209831</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868687</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868687</idno>
            <idno type="VID">167145</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A84168)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 167145)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 117:E763[11])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An apology for the royal party: written in a letter to a person of the late Councel of State. / By a lover of peace and of his country. With a touch at the pretended plea for the army.</title>
                  <author>Evelyn, John, 1620-1706.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno Dom. MDCLIX. [1659]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"A lover of peace and of his country" = John Evelyn.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Apparently a later edition of Wing E3481. In this state A3 is missigned "A2".</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "nouemb: 4th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:167145:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN APOLOGY FOR THE ROYAL PARTY: Written in a LETTER To a Perſon of the Late COUNCEL of STATE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By a Lover of Peace and of his Country.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>WITH A TOUCH At the Pretended PLEA FOR THE ARMY.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anno Dom. MDCLIX.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:167145:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:167145:2"/>
            <head>AN APOLOGIE FOR THE ROYAL PARTY: Written in a LETTER to a Perſon of the late <hi>CO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NCEL</hi> of <hi>STATE,</hi> By a Lover of Peace and of his Countrey: VVith a Touch at the <hi>pretended Plea</hi> for the Army.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He many Civilities which you are ſtill pleaſed to continue to me, and my very great deſire to anſwer them in the worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt teſtimonies of my zeal for your ſervice, muſt make my beſt Apology for this manner of Addreſſe; if out of an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream affection for your nobleſt Intereſt, I ſeem tranſported a little upon your firſt reflections, and am made to deſpiſe the conſequence of entertaining you with ſuch Truths, as are of the greateſt danger to my Self; but of no leſſe import to your happineſs, and, which carry with them the moſt indelible Characters of my Friendſhip. For if as the Apoſtle affirms, <hi>For a good man, ſome would even dare to dy,</hi> why ſhould my Charity be prejudged, if hoping to convert you from the errour of your way, I deſpair not of rendring you the Perſon for whoſe preſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on there will be nothing too dear for me to expoſe?</p>
            <p>I might with reaſon beleive that the firſt election of the Party wherein you ſtood engaged, proceeded from inexperience and the miſtake of your zeal; not to ſay from your compliances to the paſſions of others; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I both knew your education, and how obſequious you have alwayes ſhewed your ſelf to thoſe who had then the direction of you: But, when after the example of their converſion, upon diſcovery of the Impoſtures which perverted them; and the ſignall indignation of God, upon the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall Periods which your eyes have lately beheld, of the bloudieſt Tyra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, and moſt prodigious oppreſſors that ever any age of the world pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd, I ſee you ſtill perſiſt in your courſe, and that you have turn'd about with every revolution which has hapned: when I conſider, what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictions you have ſwallowed, how deeply you have ingaged, how ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilely you have flatter'd, and the baſe, and mean ſubmiſſions by which
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:167145:3"/>
you have diſhonour'd your ſelf, and ſtained your noble Family; not to mention the leaſt refinement of your religion or morality (beſides that you have ſtill preſerved a civility for me, who am ready to acknowledge it, and never merited other from you) I ſay, when I ſeriouſly reflect upon all this; I cannot but ſuſpect the integrity of your procedure, deplore the ſadneſs of your condition, and reſolve to attempt the diſcovery of it to you, by all the inſtances, which an affection perfectly touch't with a zeal for your eternall intereſt can produce. And who can tell, but it may pleaſe Almighty God, to affect <hi>you</hi> yet by a weak inſtrument, who have reſiſted ſo many powerfull indications of his diſpleaſure at your proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, by the event of things?</p>
            <p>For, ſince you are apt to recriminate, and after you have boaſted of the proſperity of your cauſe, and the thriving of your Wickedneſs (an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument farr better becoming a <hi>Mahumetan</hi> then a <hi>Christian</hi>) let us ſtate the matter a little, and compare particulars together; let us go back to the ſource, and ſearch the very principles; and then ſee, if ever any cauſe had like ſucceſſe indeed; and whether it be a juſt reproach to your Enemies, that the judgments of God have begun with them, whilſt you know not yet, where they may determine.</p>
            <p>Firſt then, be pleaſed to look North-wards upon your Bretheren the Scots,<note place="margin">Richlieu</note> who (being firſt inſtigated by that crafty <hi>Cardinal</hi> to diſturb the groth of the incomparable <hi>Church of England,</hi> and ſo conſequently the tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quility of a Nation, whoſe expedition at the Iſle of <hi>Re,</hi> gave terrour to the French) made Reformation their pretence, to gratifie their owne avarice, introduce themſelves, and a more then <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> Tyranie, impoſing upon the Church and ſtate, beyond all impudence or example. I ſay, look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on what they have gotten, by deceiving their Brethren, ſelling their King, betraying his ſon, and by all their perfidie; but a ſlavery more then <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptian,</hi> and an infamy as unparalled, as their treaſon and ingratitude.</p>
            <p>Look nerer home on thoſe whom they had ingaged amongſt us here, and tell me if there be a Perſon of them left, that can ſhew me his prize, unleſſe it be that of his Sacriledg, which he, or his Nephews muſt certainly vomite up again: What is become of this ignorant and furious zeal, this pretence of an univerſall perfection in the Religious and the Secular, after all that blood and Treaſure, Rapine and Injuſtice, which has been exhauſted, and perpetrated by theſe ſons of Thunder? Where is the King, whom they ſwear to make ſo glorious, but meant it in his <hi>Martyrdome?</hi> Where is the Claſſis, and the Aſſembly, the Lay-elder; all that geare of Scotiſh diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, and the fine new Trinkets of Reformation? Were not all theſe ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken out of their hand, while now they were in the height of their pride and triumph? And their dull Generall made to ſerve the execution of their Soveraign, and then to be turnd of himſelf as a property no more of uſe to their deſignes? Their riches, and their ſtrength in which they truſted, and the Parliament which they even idoliz'd, in ſum, the prey they had
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:167145:3"/>
contended for at the expence of ſo much ſin and damnation, ſeizd upon by thoſe very inſtruments, which they had raiſ'd to ſerve their inſatiable avarice, and prodigious diſloyalty. For ſo it pleaſed God to chaſtiſe their implacable perſecution of an excellent Prince, with a ſlavery under ſuch a <hi>Tyrant,</hi> as not being contented to butcher even ſome upon the Scaffold, ſold divers of them for ſlaves, and others he exild into cruell baniſhment, without pretence of Law, or the leaſt commiſeration; that thoſe who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore had no mercy on others, might find none themſelves; till upon ſome hope of their repentance, and future moderation, it pleaſed God to put his hook into the noſtrills of that proud <hi>Leviathan,</hi> and ſend him to his place, after he had thus mortified the fury of the Presbyterians. For un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe God himſelf ſhould utter his voice from Heaven, <hi>yea, and that a mighty voice,</hi> can there any thing in the world be more evident, then his indignation at thoſe wretches and bare fact Impoſtors, who, one after ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, uſurped upon us, taking them off at the very point of aſpiring, and praecipitating the glory and ambition of theſe men, before thoſe that where, but now, their adoarers, and that had proſtituted their conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to ſerve their luſts? To call him the <hi>Moſes,</hi> the <hi>Man of God,</hi> the <hi>Joſhua,</hi> the <hi>Saviour</hi> of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> and after all this, to treat the <hi>Thing</hi> his ſon with addreſſes no leſſe then blaſphemous, whoſe Father (as themſelves confeſs to be the moſt infamous Hypocrite and proflegate Atheiſt of all the Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers that ever any age produc'd) had made them his Vaſſalls, and would have intaild them ſo to his poſterity for ever?</p>
            <p>But behold the ſcean is again changed, not by the Royall party, the Common Enemy, or a forreign power; but by the deſpicable <hi>Rumpe</hi> of a Parliament, which that <hi>Mountebanke</hi> had formerly ſerv'd himſelf of, and had rais'd him to that pitch, and inveſtiture: But ſee withall, how ſoon theſe triflers and puppets of policy are blown away, with all their pack of modells and childiſh <hi>Chimaeras,</hi> nothing remaining of them but their Coffine, guarded by the Souldiers at Weſtminſter; but which is yet leſſe empty then the heads of thoſe Polititians, which ſo lately ſeemed to fill it.</p>
            <p>For the reſt, I deſpiſe to blot paper with a recitall of thoſe wretched <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terludes, Farces and Fantaſms,</hi> which appear'd in the ſeverall intervalls; becauſe they were nothing but the effects of an extream gyddineſs, and unparallel'd levity. Yet theſe are thoſe various deſpenſations and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>videncens in your journey to that <hi>holy land</hi> of purchaſes and profits, to which you have from time to time appeal'd for the juſtification of your proceedings, whilſt they were, indeed, no other then the manifeſt judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God upon your rebellion and your ambition: I ſay nothing of your hypocriticall faſts, and pretended humiliations, previous to the ſucceeding plots, and ſuppoſitions Revelations, that <hi>the godly might fall into the hands of your Captains,</hi> becauſe they were bugbears, and became ridiculous even to the common people.</p>
            <p>And now <hi>Sr.</hi> if you pleaſe, let us begin to ſet down the product and ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:167145:4"/>
the ſucceſſe of your party; and after all theſe faces and vertigo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, tell me ingenuouſly, if the ſingle chaſtiſment with is fallen up one afflicted man, and his loyall ſubjects, diſtreſſed by the common event of wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> want of treaſure, the ſeizure of his Fleet, forcing him from his City, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> all the diſadvantages that a perfidious people could imagine; but in fin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the crowning him with a glorious <hi>Martyrdome</hi> for the Church of God, and the liberty of his people (for which his blood doth yet cry aloud for vengeance) be comparable to the confuſion which you (that have been the conquerours) have ſuffered, and the ſlavery which you are like to leave to the poſterities which will be born but to curſe you, and to groan under the preſſures which you bequeath to your own fleſh and blood? For to what a condition you have already reduced this once flouriſhing kingdom, ſince all has been your own, let the intollerable<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> oppreſſions, taxes, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes, ſequeſtrations, confiſcations, plunders, cuſtomes, decimations, not to mention the plate, even to very thimbles and the bodkins (for even to theſe did your avarice deſcend) and other booties, ſpeak: All this diſſipated and ſquandred away, to gratifie a few covetous and ambitious wretches, whoſe appetites are as deep as hell, and as inſatiable as the grave; as if (as the Wiſe-man ſpeaks) <hi>our time here were but a market for gain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Look then into the Churches, and the manners of the people, even a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt your own <hi>Saints,</hi> and tell me, if ſince <hi>Simon Magus</hi> was upon the earth, there were ever heard of ſo many <hi>Schiſmes,</hi> and <hi>Hereſies,</hi> of <hi>Jewes</hi> and <hi>Socinians, Quakers, Fifth-monarchy-men, Arians, Anabaptiſts, Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendents,</hi> and a thouſand ſeverall ſorts of <hi>Blaſphemies</hi> and profeſſed <hi>Atheiſts,</hi> all of them ſpawned under your goverment; and then tell me what a Reformation of Religion you have effected?</p>
            <p>Was there ever in the whole Earth (not to mention Chriſtendom alone) a perjury ſo prodigious, and yet ſo avowed as that by which you have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away the eſtate of my L. <hi>Craven,</hi> at which the very <hi>Infidels</hi> would bluſh, a <hi>Turke</hi> or <hi>Sythian</hi> ſtand amaz'd?</p>
            <p>Under the Sun was it never heard, that a man ſhould be condemned for tranſgreſſing no law, but that which was made after the fact, and abrogated after execution; that the Poſterities to come might not be witneſſes of your horrid injuſtice: Yet thus you proceeded againſt my L. <hi>Stafford.</hi> How many are thoſe gallant perſons whom after articles of war, you have butchered in cold-blood, violating your promiſes againſt the Lawes of all Nations civill, or barbarous; and yet thus you dealt in the caſe of my L. <hi>Capel,</hi> Sr. <hi>J. Stawell</hi> and others.</p>
            <p>Is not the whole nation become ſullen and proud, ignorant and ſuſpici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, incharitable, curſt, and in fine, the moſt depraved and perfidious under heaven? and whence does all this proceed, but from the effects of your own examples, and the impunity of evill doers?</p>
            <p>I need not tell you how long Juſtice has been ſold by the <hi>Comittes,</hi> and the Chair-men, the Sequeſtrators, and Simoniacall Tryers, not to men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:167145:4"/>
the late Courtiers, and a ſwarm of <hi>Publicans</hi> who <hi>have eaten up the people as if they would eat bread.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Will you come now to the particular miſfortunes, and the evident hand of God upon you for theſe actions (for he has not altogether left us with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſome expreſs witneſſes of his diſpleaſure at your doings.) Behold then your <hi>Eſſex</hi> and your <hi>Warwick,</hi> your <hi>Mancheſter, Browne, Ferfaix,</hi> and your <hi>Waler,</hi> (whom once your Books ſtilled the <hi>Lord of Hoſts</hi>) Caſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heered, Impriſoned, ſuſpected and diſgraced after all their ſervices. <hi>Hotham,</hi> and his <hi>Son</hi> came to the block: <hi>Stapleton</hi> had the buriall of an Aſſe; and was thrown into a towne Ditch. <hi>Brooks</hi> and <hi>Hamden</hi> ſignally ſlain in the very act of rebellion and Sacriledge; your atheiſtical <hi>Doriſlaw, Aſcam,</hi> and the Sodomiticall <hi>Ariba,</hi> whom though they eſcaped the hand of Juſtice, yet <hi>Vengeance</hi> would not ſuffer to live: What become of <hi>Rainſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burrow? Ireton</hi> periſhed of the Plague, and <hi>Hoyle</hi> hanged himſelf; <hi>Staplie</hi> died mad, and <hi>Cromewell</hi> in a fit of rageing; and if there were any others worthy the taking notice of, I ſhould give you a liſt of their names and of their deſtinies, but it was not known whence they came which ſucceeded them; nor had they left any memory behind them, but for their ſignall wickedneſſes, as he that ſet on fire the <hi>Epheſian Temple</hi> to be recorded a Villain to poſterity. Whereas thoſe noble ſouls whom your inhumanity, (not your vertue) betraied, gave proof of their extraction, Innocency, Religion and Conſtancy under all their Tryalls and Tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors; and thoſe that died by the ſword, fell in the bed of honour, and did worthily for their Countrey; their <hi>Loyalty</hi> and their <hi>Religion,</hi> will be renowned in the <hi>Hiſtory</hi> of Ages, and precious to their memory, when your names will rot with your Carcaſſes, and your remembrance be as dung upon the face of the earth. For there is already no place of <hi>Europe</hi> where your infamy is not ſpread, whilſt your perſecuted Brethren rejoyce in their ſufferings, can abound, and can want, bluſh not at their actions, nor are aſhamed at their addreſſes, becauſe they have ſuffered for that which their Faith and their Birth, their Lawes, and their liberties have celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the moſt glorious Inſcriptious, and everlaſting Elogies,</p>
            <p>And if freſher inſtances of all theſe particulars be required, caſt but your eye a little upon the <hi>Armies pretended plea,</hi> which came lately a birding to beat the away before them, charm the ears of the vulgar, and captivate the people; That after all its <hi>Pſeudo-politicks</hi> and irreligious Principles, is at laſt conſtrained to acknowledg your open and prodigious violations, <hi rend="margQuotes">ſtrang and illegall actions, (as in termes it confeſſes) of taking up armes, raiſing and forming Armies againſt the King, fighting againſt his perſon, impriſoning, impeaching, arraigning, trying, and execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting him: baniſhing his Children, aboliſhing Biſhops, Deans and Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; taking away Kingly Government, and the Houſe of Lords, break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the crowns, ſelling the Jewells, Plate, Goods, Houſes and Lands belonging unto the Kings of this Nation, erecting extraordinary High-Courts
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:167145:5"/>
of Juſtice and therein impeaching, araigning, condemning, and executing many <hi>pretended</hi> notorious Enemies to the publique peace; when the lawes in being, and the ordinary Courts of Juſtice could not reach them: by ſtrange and unknown practiſes in this Nation, and not at all juſtifiable by any known lawes and ſtatutes,</hi> but by certain diabo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall principles of late diſtilled into ſome perſons of the Army, and which he would intitle to the whole, who (abating ſome of their Commanders, that have ſucked the ſweet of this doctrine) had them never ſo much as entred into their thoughts, nor could they be ſo depraved, though they were Maſters only of the Light of nature to direct them. For Common ſenſe will tell them, that whoever are our lawfull ſuperiours, and inveſted with the ſupream Authority, either by their own vertue, or the peoples due election, have then a juſt right to challeng ſubmiſſion to their precepts, and that we acquieſce in their determinations; ſince there is in nature no other expedient to preſerve us from everlaſting confuſion: But it is the height of all impertinency to conceive, that thoſe which are a part of themſelves, and can in ſo great a body, have no other intereſts, ſhould fall into ſuch exorbitabitant contradiction to their own good, as a child of four years old would not be guilty of; and as this Phamphleter wildly ſuggeſts in pp. 6. 11. 27. &amp;c. did they ſteer their courſe by the known lawes of the Land, and as obedient Subjects ſhould do, who without the King and his Peers, are but the Carcaſs of a Parliament, as deſtitute of the Soul which ſhould informe and give it being. But if ſo ſmall a handfull of men as appeared in the Palace-Yard without conſent of a quarter of the Engliſh Army, much leſſe of the tenthouſandth part of the free people that are not clad in red, ſhall diſturb and alter a Government when it thinkes fit to ſet aſide a few imperious officers, who plainly ſeek themſelves, and derive their Commiſſions from a ſuperiour to whom they ſwear obedience, (I mean not here the Rumpe) who ſhall ever hope, or live to ſee any go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment eſtabliſhed in theſe miſerably abuſed Nations? For I dare report my ſelf to the ingenuity of the very Souldiers themſelves, if they, who have effected all theſe changes by your wretched inſtigations, and blind pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, imagine themſelves the people of this Nation, but as a very ſmall portion of them, compared to the whole, and who are maintained by them, to recover and protect the Civill Government, according to the good old lawes of the Land; not ſuch as they themſelves ſhall invente from day to day, or as the intereſts of ſome few perſons may engage them.</p>
            <p>But if the eſſential end of Rulers be the common peace, and their Laws obliging as they become relative: reſtore us then to thoſe under which we lived with ſo much ſweetneſſe and tranquility, as no age in the world, no government under Heaven could ever pretend the like. And if the people (as you declare) are to be the Judges of it, ſummon them together in a Free Parliament, according to its legal Conſtitution; or make a univerſal <hi>Balott,</hi> and then let it appear, if <hi>Collonel Lambert</hi> and half a dozen Officers,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:167145:5"/>
with all their ſeduced Partizans, make ſo much as a ſingle <hi>Cypher</hi> to the <hi>Summe Total.</hi> And this ſhall be enough to anſwer thoſe devious Principles ſet down in the Porch of that ſpecious Edifice; which being erected upon the Sand, will (like the reſt that has been <hi>daubed with untempered mortar</hi>) ſink alſo at the next high winde that blowes upon it. But I am glad it is at laſt avowed, upon what pretexts that late pretended Parliament have pleaded on the behalf of themſelves and party, their diſcharge from all the former Proteſtations, Engagements, ſolemn Vows, Covenants, with hands (as you ſay) lift up to the moſt high God, as alſo their Oaths and Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance, &amp;c. becauſe I ſhall not in this diſcourſe be charged with ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering of them, and that the whole World may deteſt the Actions of ſuch perfidious Infidels, with whom nothing ſacred has remained inviolable.</p>
            <p>But there is yet a piece of Artifice behinde, of no leſs conſequence then the former, and that is, a ſeeking to perſwade the preſent Armie, that <hi>They</hi> were the men, who firſt engaged thus ſolemnly to deſtroy the Government under which they were born, and reduce it to this miſerable condition: whereas it is well known by ſuch as converſe daily with them, that there is hardly one of ten amongſt them, who was then in Arms, and that it was the Zelots under <hi>Eſſex, Mancheſter, Waller,</hi> and the ſucceeding Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals, who were the perſons of whoſe perfidiouſneſs he makes ſo much uſe of, and that the preſent Army conſiſt of a far more ingenuous ſpirit, and might in one moment vindicate this aſperſion, make their conditions with all advantage, and theſe nations the moſt happy people upon the Earth, as it cannot be deſpaired but they will one day do, when by the goodneſs of Almighty God, they ſhall perfectly diſcern through the miſt which you have caſt upon their eyes, leſt they ſhould diſcover the Impoſture of theſe <hi>Egyptian</hi> Sorcerers.</p>
            <p>But now he comes next to glorifie the late Northern Expedition, and becauſe it ſhould look more dreadful, he reckons up a horrible Plot of the poor <hi>Cavaliers</hi> conſpiring with Sir <hi>Geo. Booth;</hi> whereas (God knows) 'twas a thing wholly mannaged by ſome of their own party, whom the Rump had diſobliged, and that could have no other effect, then to ſhew the judgements of God, upon ſo many as it involved under a Calamity, which their former Actions had deſerved; though, under the pretence of it, and becauſe there was want of prey, many innocent perſons were ſeiz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon, and impriſoned with them.</p>
            <p>And now, <hi>Sir,</hi> if after all this injuſtice, and impiety on your parts, you have proſecuted that with the extreameſt madneſs, which you eſteemed criminal in your enemies, <hi>viz. To arrogate the ſupream power to a ſingle per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, condemn men without Law, execute, and proſcribe them with as little: Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prest for your Service, violate your Parliaments, diſpenſe with your ſolemn Oaths;</hi> in ſumme, <hi>to mingle Earth and Heaven by your unarbitrary proceedings:</hi> All which, not only your printed books, this pretended <hi>plea;</hi> but your Actions have abundantly declared; have you not juſtified the Royal party, and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:167145:6"/>
pronounced them the only honeſt men which have appeared upon the ſtage, in Characters as plain, that he which runs may read, whilſt yet you perſecute them to the death? <hi>Therefore, thou art inexcuſable, O man, that</hi> perpetrateſt <hi>theſe things; For wherein thou judgeſt another, thou condemnest thy ſelf; ſeeing thou that judgeſt doeſt the ſame things. But thinkeſt thou this, O man, that thus judgest them which do ſuch things, and doeſt the ſame, that thou ſhalt eſcape the</hi> vengeance <hi>of God? I tell ye nay, but except ye repent, ye ſhall all likewiſe periſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Truly, <hi>Sir,</hi> when I compare theſe things together, and compare them I do very often, conſider the purchaſes which you have made, and the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation you have certainly adventured; the deſpite you have done to the name of Chriſt, the Laws of Common humanity which you have violated, the malice and the folly of your proceedings; in fine, the confuſion which you have brought upon the Church, the State, and your ſelves; I adore the juſt and righteous judgment of God; and (howſoever you may poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly emerge, and recover the preſent rout) had rather be a ſufferer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt thoſe whom you have thus afflicted, and thus cenſure, then to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy the pleaſures of your ſins for that ſeaſon you are likely to poſſeſs them: For if an Angel from heaven ſhould tell me you had done your duties, I would no more believe him, then if he ſhould preach another Goſpel, then that which has been delivered to us; becauſe you have blaſphemed that holy Profeſſion, and done violence to that Gracious Spirit, by whoſe ſacred dictates you are taught to live in obedience to your Superiours, and in Charity to one another; covering yet all this <hi>Hydra</hi> of Impoſtures with a mask of Piety and Reformation, whilſt you breath nothing but oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and lie in wait to deceive. But <hi>O God! how long ſhall the Adverſary do this diſhonour, how long ſhall the Enemy blaſpheme thy name, for ever? They gather them together against the ſoul of the Righteous, and condemn the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent blood. Lo theſe are the ungodly, theſe proſper in the world, and theſe have riches in poſſeſſion: And I ſaid, then have I cleanſed my heart in vain, and waſhed my hands in innocency. Yea, and I had almoſt ſaid as they; but lo, then I ſhould have condemned the generation of thy Children. Then thought I to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand this, but it was too hard for me, until I went into the Sanctuary of God; then underſtood I the end of theſe men. Namely, how thou doſt ſet them in ſlip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery places, caſteſt them down and deſtroyest them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>O how ſuddenly do they conſume, periſh, and come to a fearful end!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We have ſeen it, indeed <hi>Sir,</hi> we have ſeen it, and we cannot but acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge it the very finger of God, <hi>mirabile in oculis nostris;</hi> and is that, truly, which even conſtrains me out of Charity to your Soul, as well as out of a deep ſenſe of your Honour, and the Friendſhip which I otherwiſe bear you, to beſeech you to re-enter into your ſelf, to abandon thoſe falſe Principles, to withdraw your ſelf from theſe Seducers, to repent of what you have done, <hi>and ſave your ſelf from this untoward generation:</hi> There is yet a door of Repentance open, do not provoke the Majeſtie of the great
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:167145:6"/>
God any longer, which yet tenders a Reconciliation to you. Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber what was once ſaid over the periſhing <hi>Jeruſalem. How often would have gathered you together, as a hen doth gather her brood under her wing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and ye would not? Behold, your</hi> Houſe <hi>is left unto you deſolate.</hi> — For <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> not think it impoſſible, that we ſhould become the moſt abandon'd, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> barbarous of all the nations under heaven. You know who has ſaid i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>He turneth a fruitfull land into a Wilderneſſe, for the iniquity of them that i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> habit therein.</hi> And truly, he that ſhall ſeriouſly conſider the ſad <hi>Carast<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3+ letters">
                     <desc>•••…</desc>
                  </gap>phe</hi> of the <hi>Eastern Empire,</hi> ſo flouriſhing in piety, policy, knowledg, liter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture, and all the excellencies of a happy and bleſſed people; would almo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> think it impoſſible, that in ſo few years, and a midſt ſo glorious a light learning and Religion, ſo ſuddain, and palpable a darkneſſe, ſo ſtran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                  <desc>••…</desc>
               </gap> and horrid a barbarity ſhould over-ſpread them, as now we behold in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> that goodly tract of the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> dominions: And what was the cauſe of a this, but the giddineſſe of a wanton people, the Schiſms and the Hereſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> in the church, and the proſperous ſucceſſes of a rebellious <hi>Imposto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> whoſe ſteps we have purſued in ſo many pregnant inſtances, giving cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance to thoſe unheard of impieties, and deluſions, as if God be not in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>finitely merciful, muſt needs involve us under the ſame diſaſters? For, whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t there is no order in the Church, no body of Religion agreed upon, no go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment eſtabliſhed, and that every man is abandon'd to his own decei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full heart: whilſt learning is decried, and honeſty diſcountenanc'd, rapit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> defended, and vertue finds no advocate; what can we in reaſon expect<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> but the moſt direfull expreſſions of the wrath of God, a univerſall deſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, when by the induſtry of <hi>Sathan</hi> and his crafty Emiſaries, ſome deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate <hi>enthuſiaſme,</hi> compounded (like that of <hi>Mohomet,</hi>) of Arian, Socinian, Jew Anabaptiſt, and the impurer <hi>Gnoſtick,</hi> ſomething I ſay made up of all theſe hereſies, ſhall diffuſe it ſelf over the Nation, in a univerſall conta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and nothing leſſe appear then the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> which we have ingrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully renounced?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For this plague is already beginning amongſt us, and there is none to take the Cenſer, and to stand between the living and the dead, that we be not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed as in a moment; for there is wrath gone out from the Lord.</hi> Let us then <hi>depart from the tents of theſe wicked men</hi> (who have brought all this upon us) <hi>and touch nothing of theirs, least we be conſumed in all their ſins.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But you will ſay, the King is not to be truſted: judg not of others by your ſelves; did ever any man obſerve the leaſt inclination of revenge in his breaſt? has he not beſides the innate propenſity of his own nature to gentleneſſe, the ſtrict injunctions of a dying Father and a <hi>Martyr,</hi> to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give even greater offenders then you are? Yes, I dare pronounce it with confidence, and avouch it whith all aſſurance, that there is not an individu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all all amongſt you, whoſe crimes are the moſt crimſon, whom he will not be moſt ready to pardon, and graciouſly receive upon their repentance; nor any thing that can be deſired of him, to which he would not cheerfully
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:167145:7"/>
accommode, for the ſtopping of that torrent of blood, and extream confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which has hitherto run, and is yet imminent over us. Do but reaſon a little with your ſelf, and conſider ſadly, whether a young Prince, mortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by ſo many afflictions, diſciplin'd by much experience, and inſtructed by the miſcarriages of others, be not the moſt excellently qualified to govern and reduce a people, who have ſo ſucceſſeſly tried ſo many governments, of old, impious and crafty Foxes, that have exerciſed upon us the moſt intol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable Tyranies that were ever heard of?</p>
            <p>But you object further, that he has lived amongſt Papiſts, is vitiouſly inclin'd, and has wicked men about him: What can be ſaid more unjuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, what more malitious? And can <hi>you</hi> have the foreheads to tell us he has lived amongſt Papiſts to his prejudice, who have proſcrib'd him from Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, perſecuted him from place to place, <hi>as a Patridg on the Mountains?</hi> You may remember who once went to <hi>Achich the King of Gath, and chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his behaviour before them, and fain'd himſelf mad in their hands;</hi> had many great infirmities, and <hi>was yet a man after Gods own heart;</hi> Whilſt the Catholick King was your Allie, you had nothing to do with Papiſts, it was then no crime: <hi>God is not mocked, away with this reſpect of perſons:</hi> But where is it you would have him to be? The <hi>Hollander</hi> dares not afford him harbour, leſt you refuſe them yours: The <hi>French</hi> may not give him bread for fear of offending you; and unleſſe he ſhould go to the <hi>Indies,</hi> or the <hi>Turk</hi> (where yet your malice would undoubtedly reach him) where can he be ſafe from your revenge? But ſuppoſe him in a Papiſt Countrey, conſtrained thereto by your incharity to his Soul as well as body; would he have condeſcended to half ſo much, as you have offered for a tolerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Papiſts, he needed not now have made uſe of this Apology, or want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the aſſiſtance of the moſt puiſſant Princes of <hi>Christendome</hi> to reſtore him, of whom he has refuſed ſuch conditions as in prudence he might have yielded to, and the people would have gladly received; whilſt thoſe who know with what perſons you have tranſacted, what truck you have made with the <hi>Jeſuites,</hi> what ſecret Papiſts there are amongſt you, may eaſily divine why they have been no forwarder to aſſiſt him, and how far diſtant he is from the leaſt wavering in his Faith. But ſince you have now declared that you will tollerate all Religions, without exception; do not think it a ſin in him, to gratifie thoſe that ſhall moſt oblige him.</p>
            <p>For his vertues and Morality, I provoak the moſt refined Family in this Nation to produce me a Relation of more piety and moderation; ſhew me a Fraternity more ſpotleſſe in their honour, and freer from the exorbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tances of youth, then theſe three Brothers, ſo conſpicuous to all the world for their Temperance, Magnanimity, Conſtancy, and Underſtanding; a friendſhip and humility unparallel'd and rarely to be found amongſt the ſevereſt p rſons, ſcarcely in a private family. It is the malice of a very black Soul, and a virulent <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>egado</hi> (of whom to be commended were the utmoſt infamy) that has interpreted ſome compliances, to which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:167145:7"/>
in diſtreſs are ſometimes engaged, with thoſe whom they converſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, to his Majeſties diſadvantage: <hi>whilſt theſe filthy dreamers defile the fleſh them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and thinking it no ſin to deſpiſe dominion, ſpeak evill of dignities, and of the things which they know not. But woe unto them, for they have gone in the way of Kain, and run greedily after the errour of Balaam, for reward, having mens perſons in admiration becauſe of advantage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the reſt, I ſuppoſe the ſame was ſaid of Holy <hi>David,</hi> when in his extream calamity, he was conſtrain'd to fly from <hi>Saul. For every one that was in diſtreſſe, and every one that was in debt, and every one that was diſcontented, gathered themſelves unto him, and he became Captain over them.</hi> And to this retinue, has your malice and perſecution reduced this excellent Prince; but he that preſerv'd him in the Wood, <hi>and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered David out of all his troubles,</hi> ſhall likewiſe in his appointed time, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver him alſo out of theſe diſtreſſes.</p>
            <p>I have now anſwered all your calumnies, and have but a word to add, that I may yet incline you to accept of your beſt intereſt, and prevent that dreadfull ruine which your obſtinacy does threaten. Is it not as perſpicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous as the Sun, that it lies in your power to reform his Counſell, intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce your ſelves, make what compoſition you can deſire, have all the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity that mortall men can imagine, and the greateſt Princes of Europe to engage in the performance? This were becoming worthy men, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable indeed; this ingenuous ſelf-denyall: And it is no diſgrace to reforme a miſtake, but to perſiſt in it lyes the ſhame. The whole Nation require it of you, and the lawes of God command it, you cannot, you muſt not deferr it. For what can you pretend that will not then drop into your boſomes? The humble man will have repoſe, the aſpiring and am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious, honours: The Merchant will be ſecure, Trades immediately reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, Aliances will be confirm'd, the Lawes reflouriſh, tender Conſciences conſider'd, preſent purchaſers ſatisfied; The Souldier payed, maintained and provided for; and what's above all this, Chriſtianity and Charity will revive again amongſt us, <hi>Mercy and Truth will meet together; righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs and peace ſhall kiſs each other.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But let us now conſider on the other ſide, the confuſion, which muſt of neceſſity light upon us if we perſiſt in our rebellion and obſtinacy; We are already impoveriſht, and conſum'd with war and the miſeries that at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend it; you have waſted our treaſure, and deſtroyed the Woods, ſpoyled the Trade, and ſhaken our properties; a univerſall animoſity is in the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry bowells of the Nation; the Parent againſt the Children, and the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren againſt the Parents, betraying one another to the death; in ſumme, if that have any truth which our B. Saviour has himſelf pronounced, <hi>That a Kingdome divided cannot stand,</hi> it is impoſſible we ſhould ſubſiſt in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition we are reduc'd to. Conſider we again, how ridiculous our late pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings have made us to our neighbours round about us. Their <hi>Miniſters</hi> laugh at our extram giddineſſe, and we ſeem to mock at their addreſſes:
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:167145:8"/>
for no ſooner do their <hi>Credentialls</hi> arrive, but behold the ſcean is changed, and the Government is fled, he that now acted King, left a fool in his place, and they ſtand amazed at our <hi>Buffoonery</hi> and madneſſe.</p>
            <p>What then may we imagine will be the product of all theſe diſadvanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, when the Nations that deride and hate us, ſhall be united for our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction; and that the harveſt is ripe for the ſickle of their fury? ſhall we not certainly be a prey to an inevitable ruine, having thus weakned our ſelves by a brutiſh civill war, and cut off thoſe glorious <hi>Heros,</hi> the wiſe and the valiant, whoſe couragein ſuch a calamity we ſhall in vain imploar, that would bravely have ſacrificed themſelves for our delivery? Let us remember how often we have ſerved a forraign people, and that there is nothing ſo confident, but a provoaked God can overthrow.</p>
            <p>For my part, I tremble, but to conſider what may be the iſſue of theſe things, when our iniquities are full, and that God ſhall make inquiſition for the bloud that has been ſpilt; unleſſe we ſuddainly meet him by an unfained repentance, and turn from all the abominations by which we have provoaked him; And then, it is to be hoped, that he who would have compounded with the <hi>Father of the faithfull,</hi> had there been but ten Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous men in <hi>Sodom;</hi> and that ſpared <hi>Nineveh</hi> that populous and great City; will yet have mercy on us, hearken to the prayers, and have regard to the teares, of ſo many Millions of people, who day and night do interceed with him: The <hi>Prieſts</hi> and Miniſters <hi>of the Lord weeping between the porch and the Altar, and ſaying, Spare thy people O Lord, ſpare thy People, and give not thine Inheritance to reproach.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now I have ſaid what was upon my Spirit for your ſake, when, for the ſatisfaction of ſuch as (through its effect upon your ſoule) this Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe of mine may poſſibly come to, I have religiouſly declared, that the Perſon who writ it, had no unworthy or ſiniſter deſign of his owne to gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie, much leſſe any other party whatever; as being neither <hi>Courtier, Souldier</hi> or <hi>Church-man,</hi> but a plain Country Gentleman, engag'd on nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide, who, has had leaſure, (through the goodneſſe of God) can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>didly, and without paſſion to examine the particulars which he has touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and expects no other reward in the ſucceſſe of it, then what <hi>Christ</hi> has promiſed in the <hi>Goſpell;</hi> The <hi>Benediction of the peace maker;</hi> and which he already feeles in the diſcharge of his Conſcience; being for his own particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, long ſince reſolv'd with himſelf, to perſiſt in his Religion, and his loyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to the death, come what will; as being fully perſwaded, that all the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions, loſſes, and other accidents which may arrive him for it here, <hi>are not worthy to be compared to that eternall weight of glory which is to be revealed hereafter;</hi> and to the inexpreſſible conſolation, which it will afford on his <hi>Death-bed,</hi> when all theſe guilded pleaſures will diſappear, this noiſe, and empty pompe; when God ſhall <hi>ſet all our ſins in order before us;</hi> and when, it is certain, that the humble, and the peaceable, the charitable and the meek ſhall not looſe their reward, nor change their hopes, for all the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:167145:8"/>
Crownes and the Scepters, the Lawrells, and the Trophies, which ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious and ſelf ſeeking men contend for, with ſo much Tyranie and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice.</p>
            <p>Let them therefore no longer deceive you, dear Sr. and as the guiſe of theſe vile men is, tell you they are the Godly-party, under which for the preſent they would paſs, and <hi>courage themſelves in their wickedneſs,</hi> ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their ears, and ſhutting their eyes againſt all that has been taught and practiſed by the beſt of Chriſtians, &amp; holieſt of Saints theſe ſixteen hundred years: <hi>You ſhall know them by their fruites, do men gather Grapes of Thornes, or Figs of Thiſtles?</hi> But ſo, being miſerably gall'd with the remembrance of their impieties, and the ſteps by which they have aſcended to thoſe fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full precepices, they ſeek to allay the ſecret pangs of a gnawing worme, by adopting the moſt prodigious of their crimes into a Religion fitted for the purpoſe, and verſatile as their giddy intereſt, till at laſt, encourag'd by the number of thriving Proſelytes and ſucceſſes, they grow ſeared and confident; ſwallowing all with eaſe, and paſſing from one hereſie to another; whilſt yet they are ſtill purſued, and ſhall never be at repoſe: For Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence will at laſt awake, and then how frightful, how deplorable, yea, how inexpreſſably ſad will that day be unto them! <hi>For theſe things have they done, and I held my tongue</hi> (ſaith God) <hi>and they thought wickedly, that I am ſuch a one as themſelves; but I will reprove them and ſet before them the things that they have done. O conſider this ye that forget God, leaſt he pluck you away, and there be none to deliver you!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now <hi>Sir,</hi> you ſee the liberty which I have taken, and how farr I have adventured to teſtifie a friendſhip which I have ever profeſſed for you: I have indeed been very bold; but it was greatly requiſite; and you know that amongſt all men, there are none which more openly uſe the freedom of reprehenſion, then thoſe who love moſt: Advices are not reject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by any, but ſuch as determine to purſue their evill courſes; and the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage which I uſe, is not to offend, but to beſeech you to return. I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jure you therefore to re-enter into your ſelf, and not to ſuffer theſe mean and diſhonourable reſpects, which are unworthy your nobler ſpirit, to prompt you to a courſe ſo deform'd, and altogether unworthy your edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation and Family. Behold your friends all deploaring your misfortunes, and your Enemies even pitie you; whilſt to gratifie a few mean and deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate perſons, you cancell your duty to your prince, and disband your Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; diſhonour your name, bring ruine and infamy on your poſterity.</p>
            <p>But when all this ſhall fail (as God forbid a title of it ſhould) <hi>I</hi> have yet this hope remaining; that when you have been ſufficiently ſated with this wicked courſe, wandred from place to place, government to government, ſect to ſect, in ſo univerſal a deluge, and find no repoſe for the ſole of your foot, (as it is certain you never ſhal) you will at laſt with the peaceful <hi>Dove,</hi> return to the Arke from whence you fled, to your firſt principles, and to ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber counſels; or with the repenting <hi>Prodigall</hi> in the Goſpel, to <hi>your Father</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:167145:9"/>
which is in heaven, and to the <hi>Father of your Countrey:</hi> For in ſo doing, you ſhall not only rejoyce your ſervant, and all good men, but the very <hi>Angels</hi> which are in heaven, and who are never ſaid to rejoyce indeed, but <hi>at the Converſion of a ſinner.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>This</hi> 27. <date>
                     <hi>Octob.</hi> 1659.</date>
               </dateline>
Et tu converſus, converte Fratres.</closer>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>PSAL. 37.</bibl>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>10.</bibl> Yet a little while, and the ungodly ſhall be clean gone, thou ſhalt look after his place, and he ſhall be away.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>36.</bibl> I my ſelf have ſeen the ungodly in great power, and flouriſhing like a green Bay-tree.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>37.</bibl> I went by, and lo he was gone; I ſought him, but his place could no where be found.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>38.</bibl> Keep innocency, and take heed unto the thing that is right: For that ſhall bring a Man peace at the laſt.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <p>I requeſt the <hi>Reader</hi> to take notice, that where, mentioning the <hi>Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terian,</hi> I have let fall expreſſions, ſomewhat reliſhing of more then uſuall aſperity; I do by no means intend it to the prejudice of many of that Judgment, who were either men of peaceable ſpirits from the beginning; or that have of late given teſtimony of the ſenſe of their errour, whilſt they were abuſed by thoſe ſpecious pretences I have reproved; but I do regard them with as much charity and affection, as becomes a ſincere Chriſtian, and their Brother.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
